Guide to the Anti-Nuclear Protests Collection, 1972 - 1984
Anti-Nuclear Protests Collection, 1972 - 1984
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
1000-157
0.5
1
In the 1970s, Wesleyan University students became active against national nuclear arms polices and practices, especially those in New England. The groups of Wesleyan University students involved were the Committee on Environmental Awareness, Connecticut Citizens Conference, Nuclear Resistance Group and Students Opposed to Nuclear Arms Race. These groups organized campus wide informational meetings, showed films and actively participated in walking onto a nuclear arms site in Seabrook, New Hampshire, on April 30, 1977. Around forty Wesleyan Students, along with other activists, were arrested, and some were convicted of criminal trespass due to the April 30 protest.
The collection includes statements from the Committee on Environmental Awareness, Connecticut Citizens Conference, Nuclear Resistance Group and Students Opposed to Nuclear Arms Race. Materials include meeting minutes, flyers, notes and Wesleyan and Connecticut press on their activism and other notes and news from the groups. Campus news articles and memos provide accounts of participation in national protests and correspondence with students who were arrested for various protests.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Acquired between 1984 and 1997.
Historical Note
In 1976, a construction permit was issued for nuclear reactors on the marshes of Seabrook, New Hampshire, near a heavily populated beach community. On April 30, 1977, the Clamshell Alliance organized a protest on the grounds of these marshes calling for the state of New Hampshire and New England as a whole to be a nuclear-free zone. The 1977 Nuclear Resistance Group on Wesleyan's campus was involved in the April 30 protest. On that day, nearly 2,000 people walked onto the construction site to protest having a nuclear presence in New England. Of those 2,000 people, over 1,400 were arrested and 39 Wesleyan students were among them. In June 1977, the Clamshell Alliance held another on-site rally consisting of 20,000 participants of which several hundred also marched to Washington D.C. to protest in front of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission.
Students at Wesleyan who were arrested on April 30 were charged with criminal trespass in the Portsmouth Court and called for bail solidarity, therefore refusing to post bail until they were all released on personal recognizance. They were held for ten or eleven days, during which Wesleyan's Legal Defense and Bail Fund Board organized a fundraising drive for their release. As of May 11, thirty-two Wesleyan students were still held in state armories apparently under severe conditions; some of those arrested spent 14 hours on a cramped bus before any official arrest and some were held in a room with 691 other people.
Although Wesleyan organized a fundraiser for bail, the imprisoned students felt that it would be counterproductive. One student dictated a letter via telephone asking that the Wesleyan community help in writing letters, making phone calls and protesting the Connecticut governor if he were to accept any of the Seabrook prisoners into Connecticut jails. Some of the arrested students posted bail, and on May 13, the remaining prisoners accepted guilty pleas and were released on their own recognizance.
The Nuclear Resistance Group on Wesleyan's campus continued to stay active in the anti-nuclear front. In 1979, the group participated in another nationally recognized anti-nuclear rally in Buchanan, New York. Over two hundred protesters were arrested, Wesleyan students among them. In the early 1980s, protests were held on campus calling for a nuclear freeze.
The anti-nuclear arms groups also proposed and got approved Wesleyan as a nuclear-free zone. This was achieved in 1984 and consisted of an agreement with Wesleyan students and Wesleyan administration that the school would not participate in the production, testing, deployment, storage, or transportation of nuclear weapons. The school also agreed not to participate in research or investment associated with the development of nuclear weapons. Although this referendum was well-received by the Wesleyan community, the Board of Trustees had the final vote on the implementation of this agreement. Many believed this to be a symbolic gesture of the Wesleyan community during the Cold War, although the agreement was practical in the sense of Wesleyan refraining from investments and research related to nuclear arms. Although Wesleyan still had investments in companies that had some varied involvement in nuclear arms production or research, the campus decided to become a nuclear-free zone like many zoned areas in Europe.
Collection Overview
The collection contains folders for each of the groups represented on campus that were active in anti-nuclear arms protests. These folders contain an array of information on the groups. Memos to and from the student groups and faculty as well as documents with their budgets, meeting minutes and membership lists are all included. Many groups also have a group statement with their goals as a group along with information on the greater anti-nuclear movement.
The first folder contains information on the Committee on Environmental Awareness. It includes memos about funding, budget write-ups and allocations. It also contains the goals of the group, a letter to the College Body Committee along with flyers from the group, information on film showings and newspaper clippings and papers on their activities.
The second folder documents from the Connecticut Citizen's conference, which holds pamphlets on their conference in 1983 and pictures of students lobbying.
Folders three through eleven contain information on the Nuclear Resistance Group. Each folder is divided by document type-correspondence, articles and news on the group, notes, films, agendas etc. Folder three and four contain reports and minutes on the Nuclear Power Forum, copies of the Radioactivist Flash, and events bulletin and announcements. Folder five contains proposals, a press announcement and informational flyers on Seabrook and the Reactor Pressure Vessel. The sixth folder contains information pertaining to the Clamshell Alliance and their activities and relationship with Wesleyan. Folder seven contains information on films shown, including receipts from where the films were obtained. Folder eight consists of member information; mailing lists, directories, phone lists and meeting minutes. Folder nine includes notes about the group, letters with other coalitions and dates of correspondence and demonstrations and films. Folder ten consists of press on the group and their demonstrations while folder eleven contains group history, editorials, press release and publications and film lists.
Folder twelve is documents on the group Students Opposed to the Nuclear Arms Race. This folder has the contents of their Alternative Education Forum, flyers, letters to student activists and editors from 1984 as well as information of Nuclear Free Zone and nuclear weapons.
Collection Arrangement
Organized alphabetically by group name.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Antinuclear movement--United States.; Seabrook Nuclear Power Plant (N.H.); Student movements--United States.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Committee on Environmental Awareness
  Contains documents regarding the Committee on Environmental Awareness at Wesleyan in the 1970's including flyers, memos, budgetary information, and correspondence.
  - Wesleyan Events Calendar, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memo: second semester funding
  - Letter to the College Body Committee: request for funds
  - Budget, spring 1973
  - Letter to the College Body Committee: handwritten
  - First Semester Allocations
  - Alternative Energy Fair, 1978
  - Goals: handwritten
  - $25 gift from Sierra Club
  - BLURP: CEA Newsletter, February and March 1975
  - Environmental Film Series, winter-spring 1974
  - Newspaper clipping: Amory to Speak on Struggle of Wildlife
  - Statement: CEA Who We Are, 1974
  - Wesleyan University News Bureau, 1974
  - Symposium: Limits to Growth
  - Unlimited Growth: Growing, Growing, Gone? - F.H. Bormann
  - Newspaper clipping: Dubos States Energy Shortage Has Benefits, 1974
  - Flyer: Senator George McGovern 1972
  - Flyer: Dr. Charles Remington
  - Flyer: Meeting and election
  - Flyer: Sierra Club Films- An Island in Time and Wilderness Alps of Stehekin
  - Flyer: The Galapagos Islands
  - Flyer: Sierra Club Wilderness Films
  - Flyer: Audubon Films
  - Flyer: David Lavine, Director of the Inland Wetland Project
  - Flyer: Conference on the Environment of Lower Connecticut River Region
  - Flyer: Films Death Be Not Loud and A Question of Values
  - Business Card: Artisan Tree Care
  - Flyer: René Dubos
  - Flyer: The U.S. - Soviet Environmental Cooperation Effort
  - Folder: leaflets, articles about and by CEA
  - Alternative Energy Fair
  - Flyer: film Dawn of the Solar Age, 1977
  - Letter: to Mr. McHarg from Wesleyan CEA, 1975
  - Letter: to Justice Douglas, 1975
  - Letter: to Dr. Meadows from S. Marc Zemke, 1974
  - Letter: to Joe Broder from S. Marc Zemke, 1973
  - Letter: to Dr. Ronald Ridker from S. Marc Zemke, 1974
  - Letter: draft to Justice Douglas
  - Letter: to Steve from Barry Lenk (handwritten)
  - Paper: Energy for the Post-Fossil Fuel Era, by Beth Penney, 1975
- Connecticut Citizen's Conference
  Folder contains photos and a pamphlet from 1983.
  - 2 pictures of student lobbying, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlet: Connecticut Citizen's Conference, 1983
- Nuclear Resistance Group
  Folders three through eleven contain information on the Nuclear Resistance Group. Each folder is divided by document type, such as correspondence, articles and news on the group, notes, films, and agendas.
  - Letters, Memos, and Meeting Notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter: to advertisers from Miles Ehrlich, 1977
    - Nuclear Power Forum, group reports/minutes and attendance
    - Memo: to Wesleyan Employees from Wesleyan Workplace Committee, February, 1977
    - Announcements and notes (handwritten)
  - Newsletters (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Radioactivist Flash, 1977, February 1978-August 1978
    - Nuclear Resistance Group Bulletin- upcoming events
    - Facts on the Vermont Yankee Nuclear Power Plant/Malfunctions, 1979
  - Anti-Nuclear Information (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Group structure proposal, 1977
    - War Resisters League- Bill, 1978
    - Correspondence: The Task Force against Nuclear Pollution
    - Flyer: So what was Seabrook anyway?
    - Blockade Scenario
    - What is the Reactor Pressure Vessel?
    - Flyer: Rally
    - Flyer: Seabrook!
    - Stop the Neutron Bomb
    - Press announcement
  - Clamshell Alliance (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Clamshell Alliance: Capitol Letters
    - Correspondence: Hartford Clamshell Alliance
    - State of Connecticut Department of Utility Control: Brief of Wesleyan NRG, 1980
    - Report from Connecticut Clamshell meeting
    - Clamshell coalition minutes, 1978, 1979
    - Clamshell News: New London County, 1980
    - Hartford Clam New Years News
    - Clam Bits
    - Transportation of Nuclear Waste
    - Flyer: Public Hearing
    - Flyer: Bus to Seabrook
    - Phone Numbers, handwritten
  - Films (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Film Bills
    - Notice for Wesleyan Events Calendar
    - Film notes, handwritten
    - Letter from National Association for Foreign Student Affairs, 1974
    - U.S. Atomic Energy Commission Technical Info. Center, Film Request, 1974
    - Letter to WRC-TV, handwritten, 1974
    - Letter from Earthkeeping
  - Member Contacts (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Mailing lists
    - Directories
    - Phone lists
    - Meeting Minutes
  - Group notes (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with Coalition for a New Foreign and Military Policy
    - Note to NRG, handwritten
    - Clamshell agenda (backside notes on nuclear films, handwritten)
    - April schedule
    - Notes on dates of phone calls, handwritten, 1979
    - Notes on slideshow, demonstration and films
    - To-Do list
  - Press on N. R. G. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Argus: Anti-Nukers Rally for Reform, 1977
    - Middletown Press: 40 from Wes Join N-Plant Protest, 1977
    - Hartford Courant: Wesleyan Group in Van of Anti-Nuclear Protests, 1979
    - Hermes: Students to Join Protest against Seabrook Nuke, 1977
    - Hermes: Nuclear Foes Battle over Seabrook Site, 1976
  - Documents, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letter from Wesleyan Secretaries
    - Press Release, 1978
    - Miliston III is a Bad Investment, 1981
    - Editorial: A Day of Mourning
    - NRG History File- member list?
    - Press Release: Northeast Utilities Annual Meeting of Shareholders, 1981
    - Publications and Film Lists
- Students Opposed to the Nuclear Arms Race
  This folder has the contents of their Alternative Education Forum, flyers, letters to student activists and editors from 1984 as well as information about the Nuclear Free Zone and nuclear weapons.
  - Wesleyan Alternative Education form (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Flyers: The Draft: Information and Options
  - Letter from SONAR to Student Activists, 1984
  - Letter to Editors, 1984
  - Information on Nuclear Free Zone and Nuclear Weapons